<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An essay in morality written by G.B. to his friend H.P., Esquire ; in which the nature of virtue and vice is distinctly stated, their respective reasonableness and unreasonableness demonstrated, and several useful conclusions inferred.</title>
            <author>G. B. (George Bright), d. 1696.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1682</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 84 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 79 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A29500</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B4672</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R18007</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12395417</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12395417</idno>
            <idno type="VID">61142</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A29500)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 61142)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 271:9)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An essay in morality written by G.B. to his friend H.P., Esquire ; in which the nature of virtue and vice is distinctly stated, their respective reasonableness and unreasonableness demonstrated, and several useful conclusions inferred.</title>
                  <author>G. B. (George Bright), d. 1696.</author>
                  <author>Plumptre, Henry.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 149, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for John Wright ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1682.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The author's name appears on p. [1] at end.</note>
                  <note>According to a ms. note, H.P. stands for Henry Plumptre.</note>
                  <note>Errata: p. [2] at end.</note>
                  <note>Advertisements ([2] p.) at end.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in University of Chicago Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Ethics --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:61142:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:61142:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AN ESSAY IN Morality.</p>
            <p>Written by <hi>G. B.</hi> to his Friend <hi>H. P.</hi> Eſquire.</p>
            <p>In which the Nature of Virtue and Vice is diſtinctly ſtated, Their reſpective Reaſonableneſs and Unreaſonableneſs demonſtrated, And ſeveral uſeful Concluſions inferred.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>John Wright</hi> at the <hi>Crown</hi> on <hi>Ludgate hill.</hi> 1682.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:61142:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:61142:2"/>
            <head>The CONTENTS.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <label>
                     <hi>Artic.</hi> 1.</label> WHatever is in the Soul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of Man reduced to two Heads, <hi>viz.</hi> Action and Paſſion.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>2.</label> Action in the Soul of two ſorts, (1.) Aſſent or Judgment. (2.) Volition.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>3.</label> In Volition, Four things only to be conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered. (1.) The Faculty. (2.) The Action. (3.) An Actual Inclination. (4.) An habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Inclination.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>4.</label> Of the three laſt, the Perfection and Defect may be conſidered.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>5.</label> The Object of Volition at the ſame time but one.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>6.</label> The Object of Volition is only good of two ſorts, <hi>viz.</hi> that of the end, or delectable good; and that of the means, or profitable good.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>7.</label> The goodneſs of the Means, is the good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the End.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>8.</label> The <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, a ſort of profitable good.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>9.</label> Delectable good hath indefinite degrees in Extenſion, Intenſion, and Duration.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>10.</label> The greateſt delectable good abſolutely, is the Eternal Happineſs of the whole Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>11.</label> The firſt perfectionof Volition is to be directed to this abſolutely greateſt good.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>12.</label> That this is a perfection.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>13.</label> That it is poſſible, deſirable, may be in the higheſt degree delightful.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>14.</label> To have a leſs good than abſolutely the
<pb facs="tcp:61142:3"/>greateſt, for the Object of our Volition, is a defect.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>15.</label> This <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, or relation of Volition to its Object, is Moral good and evil.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>16.</label> This Moral good is a kind of <hi>bonum utile.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>17.</label> Sin privately an infinite evil.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>18.</label> And it may be ſo poſitively.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>19.</label> A ſecond perfection of Volition is ſtrength, force, zeal.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>20.</label> A third, Conſtancy.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>21.</label> The juſt moderation of it ſeems a fourth.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>22.</label> Moral good and evil depend not upon a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Beings's will.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>23.</label> Nor upon the freedom of Will.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>24.</label> Poſſible to will the rectitude of an action, and yet to ſin.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>25.</label> A man to be eſtimated good or bad, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his Habitual Inclination.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>26.</label> A general diſtribution of Virtues called <hi>inherent.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>27.</label> Another from the parts of the Univerſal good.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>28.</label> Theſe to be all taken together, and conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered as one.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>29.</label> 
                  <hi>Inſtrumental or eventual</hi> Virtues.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>30.</label> When it may be true, that <hi>Virtus con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtit in medio.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>31.</label> The nature and degrees of this ſort of Virtues.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>32.</label> It is not true, that <hi>Virtutes ſunt connexae.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>33.</label> How to determine which Virtues and Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces are the greateſt.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>34.</label> Actual inclinations and propenſions may be ſinful.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>35.</label> The reaſon for the manner of writing, and the Style of this Eſſay.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="essay">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:61142:3"/>
            <head>To his Honoured Friend <hi>H. P.</hi> Eſquire.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Dear Sir,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Perceive your very in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſitive and ſearch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Genius hath not permitted you to reſt ſatisfied with what hath been commonly taught and received in many Queſtions which you think of the greateſt concernment to be truly and clearly reſolved: at leaſt of much more than
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:61142:4"/>moſt of thoſe which ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily now adays employ the buſie thoughts and pens of Men. And as they have given you ſome trouble and care, ſo I underſtand by you, that they are likely to give me ſome too. For you are pleaſed to believe, that I may have been not altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a ſtranger to thoughts about ſuch matters; and that peradventure I may have fallen upon ſomething either as to Matter or Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod, or both, which might a little contribute to your light and eaſe: though I
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:61142:4"/>ſcarcely know any man who ſtands in leſs need of it than your ſelf. Perhaps our free and frequent mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Entertainments with Diſcourſes of ſuch nature (the moſt delightful and profitable uſe of friendſhip) have given occaſion to your kind opinion, and put you upon making further tryal.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sir!</hi> I muſt own it to be my Perſwaſion alſo, that the Queſtions you propoſed are all of them of impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, and ſome of them of abſolutely the greateſt; and that they ought to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:61142:5"/>with more clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, certainty, and (which is hugely conſiderable to ſhort-liv'd Mortals) with more brevity than hitherto for all't I know they have been. But I cannot own myſelf to be the perſon in Parts, Health, or Leiſure, ſo happy, as to promiſe you the performance of any great matter at preſent, whereby I might be ſervice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to you, and anſwer either your deſire or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation. Nevertheleſs, upon your Requeſt and Command, which go a
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:61142:5"/>great way with me, backed I acknowledge with ſome ſuſpicion and preſumption that ſomething might be done, I have attempted one of them, which I have been the moſt impatient to be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied in my ſelf, as appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to me of the vaſteſt conſequence, and yet de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered, as I thought (ſuch was my unquiet curioſity if you pleaſe) with but too much miſtake, confuſion, and defect in the beſt Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and of greateſt name: and therefore long and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten before I received your
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:61142:6"/>command, it had been in my thoughts. The queſtion is, what ſhould be the perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of our Active power or Will, of its Actions or Volitions, of its actual and habitual Inclinations, or in one word, of our <hi>Manners;</hi> and not only of ours, but of any intelligent being exi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtent, and therefore even of the Divine Nature it ſelf; I mean of its
<hi>Volitions</hi> and <hi>Decrees,</hi> not of any <hi>inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,</hi> which including ſome imperfection, belong not thereunto. Many in my judgment have been the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:61142:6"/>miſtakes and errors in Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinity and Natural Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phy, but eſpecially in Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rality and Politicks, for want of a right underſtanding in this Queſtion; ſome of which I am ſure, upon peruſal of this, will not eſcape your Obſervation.</p>
            <p>I have delivered what I had to ſay, in almoſt Mathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matical Method, beginning at the moſt ſimple Notions, which are the moſt plain and undoubted, and then proceeding to what is more compounded; ſo that that which follows, generally de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pends
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:61142:7"/>upon and ſuppoſeth the knowledge of what is before. I have alſo endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured that my ſtyle be ſimple, ſhort and clear, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any ornament or finery of words, which may dar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken the Senſe, or divert the Attention; though it be not ſo common, and ſometimes perhaps uncouth, for a rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon which you'l meet withal at the end of the Eſſay. But I did not think it this time expedient to go any further, than to point out the way of compoſing a Syſtem of <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thicks</hi> from theſe Principles;
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:61142:7"/>which I know at your leiſure you can eaſily do your ſelf. As for what is done, I muſt requeſt the favour of you to read over the whole, which is but ſhort, before you paſs judgement of any part, for the prevention of needleſs diſſatisfaction and ſcruple.</p>
            <p>After all, I muſt crave leave to remember ourſelves of that which we have of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten agreed in; namely, how little the cleareſt and moſt certain knowledge of theſe things will ſignifie, without the practice; and that a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerouſly
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:61142:8"/>honeſt man, whoſe Soul is animated and imbu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with Virtue, acting ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to theſe principles from a publick and univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalized ſpirit, though they lye not ſo neatly and order<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in his head, is infinitely to be preferred before a meer ſubtle, though moſt ſucceſsful Speculator, which talks as high as Heaven, whoſe Law is ſuch love, as is hereafter deſcribed, but lives as low as earth, where according to the <hi>Jewiſh A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage</hi>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>All friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip is governed by ſelf-inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt,</hi>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:61142:8"/>or rather, nothing is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved but Self, and what miniſters to its pleaſure or advantage.</p>
            <p>Though it is not to be denied neither, that naked diſcourſe and true reaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing is of very great uſe here too. For there are ſome men who believe all the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious inclinations, affections, and tempers of Mankind, to be the effect only of divers bodily tempers and exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, not at all of Reaſon and Underſtanding; and that thoſe to Vice (ſo cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led) as they are more gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:61142:9"/>ſo they are more neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary, natural, and reaſonable too, than that to what we term Virtue; which, ſay they, is againſt Nature, and ſo far from being reaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, that it is impoſſible. Now theſe men are to be convinced, if they be capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of it, or at leaſt ſilenced and confuted.</p>
            <p>Others again there are, and that of the beſt ſort of Men, who are great lovers of truth where they can diſcern it; who are ſtrange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly affected and tranſported with diſtinct and clear un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding;
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:61142:9"/>who deſire to ſee why they ſhould be more carried to one thing than another; who do not care to be born away blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with great and ſwelling paſſions, without the gui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of calm Reaſon, ſeem they never ſo natural, and even Divinely inſpired or impreſſed; who finally are very uneaſie, ſlow, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſatisfied, while they act ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norantly and blindly. In ſuch perſons, their approba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of and conſent to Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue will be more ſincere and hearty, their bent and
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:61142:10"/>tendency to it more uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form, firm and conſtant, their love more deeply rooted and embowelled, when they ſhall ſee its na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and practice demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrated and deduced from the moſt plain and evident truths.</p>
            <p>Nor are we finally to think that the principle or end of all our actions, the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Good</hi> ſo much inſiſted on in the following Eſſay, is ſuch a high-flown wide notion, and ſo much out of the view of the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerality of men, as to be of
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:61142:10"/>no uſe or application in hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane life amongſt them. For contrariwiſe, every one may, and we ſee that plain ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt men of all ranks and ſorts do propound and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue it in their little ſphere of action and comprehenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as God himſelf doth in the immenſe revolution of his providence. He that knows no more than a Neighbors Cottage or two, may have the ſame general end, namely, the greateſt good he underſtands, with him who is able to compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend the intereſt of a whole
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:61142:11"/>Nation, or of the whole World if it were poſſible. The pooreſt Vicar may un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand as well as the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended Paſtor of the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal Church, and perhaps better practice accordingly, that the only end of his Function and all his Actions, is not his own perſonal in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt only, but the honour of God, the Salvation of Souls, or the good of his Church, (and how eaſie is it to extend his Notion to the whole world?) the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful diſcharge of his duty and his reward altogether:
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:61142:11"/>and ſo the meaneſt Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chanique or dulleſt Plow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man may be eaſily taught to deſire by all his life, and particularly in his honeſt Calling, to pleaſe and ſerve God, to ſupport himſelf and Family, to ſupply and benefit his Neighbours, in hopes of Gods general bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing upon himſelf here, both in Soul and Body, and of his reward hereafter. Set but a man entirely free from himſelf, and he will have no other bounds than the moſt comprehenſive good he can reach. Nor indeed is there
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:61142:12"/>any thing which lies nearer the Mind of Man, and which he hath a more natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral inclination to believe, than that a publick good is to be preferred before a perſonal, ſuppoſing them both equal in reſpect of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenſion or degree; and why not then the moſt publick of all, <hi>viz.</hi> the good of the whole Univerſe, as it were one Corporation or Society? But I am going to prevent my ſelf, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get the bounds and deſign of a Prefatory Epiſtle.</p>
            <p>For the reſt of your
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:61142:12"/>Queſtions (you were plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to make out a ſcore, and I doubt you may have more in your Budget) I muſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat you to ſtay your ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mach a while with this Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel, and to reſpite an anſwer to them. If what I now ſend you be acceptable to ſuch a diligent, I had almoſt ſaid troubleſome enquirer, whom as I have obſerved nothing leſs will ſatisfie, than the utmoſt a man can know and ſay, you may hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter command the like Eſſay upon ſome one or more of them; which I know your
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:61142:13"/>friendſhip and goodneſs will permit me to obey, when I find my ſelf beſt able to ſerve you.</p>
            <p n="1">1. FIrſt then be pleaſed to obſerve, That all that is in the Soul of Man, may be reduced, according to <hi>Des-Cartes,</hi> to two gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral things. (1.) Paſſion. (2.) Action. The firſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains all ſorts of Percepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, <hi>viz.</hi> Senſe, Memory, Imagination, Intellection, Paſſions, or Affections; al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though there ſeems to be ſomewhat of Action too
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:61142:13"/>in the Souls Perceptions.</p>
            <p n="2">2. And as for Action, there hath ſeem'd to be of it in the Soul, theſe four kinds. (1.) Dubitation. (2.) Suſpenſion. (3.) Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent. (4.) Volition. But I rather now think only two. (1.) Aſſent. (2.) Volition. For as for Dubitation, it ſeems to be nothing but Suſpenſion; and Suſpenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſeems only an act of Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lition not to aſſent; and Nolition is but Volition of the abſence of a thing.</p>
            <p n="3">3. To ſay nothing at this time of Aſſent; in Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lition
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:61142:14"/>may be conſidered four things. (1.) The fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty of Volition, uſually called Appetite; which is but one in Man, diſtingui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed by its ſeveral Objects; as when it hath for its Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject ſenſible and corporeal good, or certain agreeable motions of the Body which cauſe the perception of pleaſure in the Soul, it is called the Senſitive Appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tite: But when it hath for its Object that which can be apprehended only by the rational faculty of the Soul, or that faculty where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:61142:14"/>the Soul perceives Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Objects (which are but of two ſorts; either abſolute, as Spiritual Subſtances and their Attributes, ſuch as Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception and Volition, Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, &amp; Power, and Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; or Relative, as the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>habitudes,</hi> and relations of things, ſuch as Means &amp; End, Likeneſs and Diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, and conſequently E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quality and Inequality) I ſay, then it may be called the Rational Appetite. Though indeed that only hath been uſed to be ſo termed, which hath for its object, <hi>Bonum
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:61142:15"/>honeſtum,</hi> the <hi>honeſty, probi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, rectitude</hi> of a mans acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that which ought to be done, or is according to true reaſon.</p>
            <p>The ſecond thing to be obſerved in Volition, is the <hi>Action;</hi> the third, An actual Inclination or Propenſion in the Soul; and the fourth, An Habitual Inclination. Of the firſt and ſecond none doubts; and for the third, experience teacheth, that there is often this which I call an <hi>Actual Inclination</hi> of the Soul to a certain object; others a <hi>Propenſion, Velleity
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:61142:15"/>hankering,</hi> before there be any expreſs Volition; that which is uſually ſignified by ſuch phraſes; <hi>I could find in my heart to do ſuch a thing;</hi> and that of <hi>Foelix</hi> to St. <hi>Paul, Thou haſt almoſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded me to be a Chriſtian.</hi> And for the fourth, this one thing evinces it, <hi>viz.</hi> That there is a great difference between men in the facili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, readineſs, and ſtrength to their actual inclinations, and Volitions, before they actually exiſt. Of this fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cility in one man, which is not in another, there muſt
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:61142:16"/>be ſome <hi>preſent</hi> cauſe in one man which is not in another; and this I call an <hi>Habitual Inclination</hi> or <hi>Volition.</hi> It is moſt certain, there is ſomething in two men ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſtomed to two things with delight, when they have no actual Inclination and Volition in them; which upon the propoſal of thoſe two different ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, doth produce two different or contrary actual Inclinations and Volitions, and this not only in the Mechaniſms of their Bodies, by which thoſe objects ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cite
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:61142:16"/>corporeal paſſions of love or delight; but in the Soul too, and moſt often contracted by the frequent actual inclinations impreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed upon the Soul by theſe paſſions, and ſometimes without them. But it is enough, that it is agreed by all men, that there is an actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al difference <hi>inherent</hi> and <hi>preſent</hi> in the Soul, between a Drunkard and an Ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious man, even when they are aſleep, or their Volition and actual inclination are employed about other things; which then appears,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:61142:17"/>when the proper objects of their reſpective appetites and habitual inclinations are propoſed to them.</p>
            <p>As for all other humane Actions, which have been called <hi>imperate,</hi> or Actions commanded by, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent upon Volition, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept Volition itſelf, (for one Volition may have for its object another Volition) ſuch as are Attention, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration, Judgment, mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the parts of the Body, or Bodily Action, in which is Speech or Words; I meddle not at preſent
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:61142:17"/>with them, only ſuggeſt, that there is nothing of Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral good or evil, of
<hi>inherent</hi> Virtue or Vice in them: they are indeed moſtwhat (though they may be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembled) ſigns thereof, and of its degrees; nor are they ſo much as what in the Twenty ninth Article or Paragraph we term <hi>inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental</hi> or <hi>eventual</hi> Virtues or Vices, any further than they include <hi>Volition.</hi> For example, there is neither Virtue nor Vice in attenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on or judgment, which are actions of the Mind; nor
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:61142:18"/>in Speech, Geſture, Motion, which are actions of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy; but only in the
<hi>Volition</hi> or act of the Will, which commands or effects them.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Now of theſe three laſt, <hi>viz.</hi> Actual Volition, Actual and Habitual Incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, the perfection and defect may be conſidered: which perfection and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect (of Volition for exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and ſo of the reſt) can be only in two reſpects, <hi>viz.</hi> (1.) Of the Object. (2.) Of the Action.</p>
            <p n="5">5. And firſt, concerning the Object of Volition, it
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:61142:18"/>is to be noted, that at the ſame time it can be but one, though that one may conſiſt of ſeveral parts which may be ſucceſſively regarded. For example, a man cannot will and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard at the ſame preciſe time his Neighbours good and his own Reputation, as two diſtinct ſeparate co-or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinate things; but he may will them both together, as making up, or compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing one entire Object; like as the Eye can ſee but one Object at the ſame time painted at the bottom there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:61142:19"/>conſiſting of many parts; the whole it may ſee together confuſedly, and but one point diſtinctly.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Moreover, that the only Object of Volition, and ſo of the reſt, is <hi>bonity</hi> or <hi>good</hi> only, not <hi>evil,</hi> is ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt from univerſal expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience. All which good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, or what is <hi>convenient, congruous, eligible, deſirable,</hi> (for by all theſe may boni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty or good be deſcribed) is of two kinds. (1.) That of the End, (2.) That of the Means. That of the End hath been uſually called
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:61142:19"/>
               <hi>jucundum,</hi> delectable or pleaſant good or pleaſure, delight: although this very <hi>pleaſure</hi> hath ſome further uſe, &amp; is likewiſe a means to excite, encourage, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie the Operations of the Mind, which again mediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and immediately may produce new pleaſure. That of the means is called <hi>bonum utile,</hi> or profitable good to obtain the end of delectable good, of which the kinds are numerous.</p>
            <p n="7">7. The goodneſs of the means is nothing but its Conducibility to, or Cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſality
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:61142:20"/>of the end; which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed is the goodneſs of the end in the means; it is the ſame: there is nothing eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gible in the means to obtain any end, but the goodneſs of the end it ſelf. Of this <hi>profitable good, bonum hone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtum,</hi> or honeſt good, is one ſort or kind, as we ſhall preſently underſtand.</p>
            <p n="8">8. And to add this for the preſent, the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or pulchritude and beauty of Virtue, in whatſoever it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts, talked of ſo much by Platoniſts, is another ſort; and is only therefore good,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:61142:20"/>becauſe it is ſo congruous or delectable an object to the Mind, or ſome way or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hath in it ſome cauſali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of pleaſure or delight.</p>
            <p n="9">9. As for <hi>delectable good,</hi> which is, as hath been ſaid, the only object of Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lition, it is better under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood by every mans expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience, than by all the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcriptions that can be given of it: ſuch as <hi>Ariſtotle</hi>'s per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of the Minds Ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration; and
<hi>Eudoxus</hi>'s per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect and grateful aſſenſion and acquieſcence; <hi>Plato's</hi> paſſion, affection, and diffu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:61142:21"/>of the mind, and the repoſe of the Will in ſome convenient good; and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny others, ſome of which are contrary each to other: as when ſome ſay it is Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and ſome ſay it is the Reſt and Repoſe of the Mind. It is more to our purpoſe to obſerve, that it hath indefinite degrees, and that in three reſpects only and no more; <hi>viz.</hi> (1.) In Extenſion as to Subjects. (2.) Intenſion. (3.) Dura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Of which (to take the extremes only) the loweſt degree in the firſt reſpect is
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:61142:21"/>the good of one ſingle Soul; the higheſt, that of all Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Beings exiſtant, uſually comprehended under God, our Neighbour, and our ſelves: where by Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, we underſtand all Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional Creatures at leaſt. We actually indeed know a moſt inconſiderable part of Mankind, only our own Family, Town, or Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey; to whoſe greateſt good notwithſtanding if we direct our Volition, it is a ſign we implicitely will that good which is abſolute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the greateſt; and that if
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:61142:22"/>any greater good were within our view and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion, we ſhould will that expreſly and actually. In the ſecond reſpect, we want both conceits and words for the loweſt and higheſt degree. In the third reſpect, the loweſt degree is that good which is mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentany, the higheſt Eternal.</p>
            <p n="10">10. Wherefore the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt delectable good abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely, is that which is ſo in extenſion, intenſion, du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration; or the <hi>Eternal hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs of the whole <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſe</hi> conſidered as one thing, and
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:61142:22"/>as <hi>Cartes</hi> conſidered Moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in the Material world.</p>
            <p n="11">11. After which it is ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie to obſerve, that the greateſt and firſt perfection of Volition in reſpect of the Object, is to be directed to this abſolutely greateſt good, or to have it for its Object: and contrariwiſe, the greateſt defect thereof is to be directed to the leaſt part thereof, in reſpect a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain of Extenſion, Intenſion, &amp; Duration; for example, to the ſmalleſt momentany pleaſure of any one ſingle being, which is uſually, if
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:61142:23"/>not always, ones ſelf.</p>
            <p n="12">12. Nor is it leſs mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt, that this is a <hi>perfection,</hi> as it is the common ſenſe of all men: for otherwiſe, to illuſtrate rather than to prove it, God would have been equally perfect if he had not, as if he had de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined to make the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe, and that in ſuch a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree happy as it is: nay, if his nature had been ſuch as to have been the moſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighted with the eternal mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery of all his Creatures, it would have been equally his perfection to have effect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:61142:23"/>it for his own pleaſure, as to have made it happy. Again, the Devil, or the moſt malicious, proud, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vengeful, finally the moſt wicked of all Natures, is therefore the moſt imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, becauſe he is the moſt pleaſed with others evil.</p>
            <p n="13">13. It hath indeed been taught by ſome of thoſe who have deduced all our Offices and duties from ſelf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>love and intereſt, that this perfection is not competible to any being whatſoever; at leaſt not to men: that every nature is neceſſarily
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:61142:24"/>carried to its own proper good only; that it cannot be in the leaſt moved with the good of another. But I contrariwiſe affirm in the firſt place, that this perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is a thing poſſible to a reaſonable Nature. Next, that there is in all men, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong other innate appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tites, this alſo of Univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal Beneficence. And final<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that there is a Capacity in our Souls of being more pleaſed and delighted there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with, than any ſingle Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject in the world, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently it is improveable
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:61142:24"/>to a higher degree of ſtrength and force (which may be called generoſity) than any other appetite whatſoever. All which, becauſe it is of greateſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence, is thus proved. (1.) That it is a thing poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible; if it be not, it is ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther becauſe we cannot will anothers good, or we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not apprehend it. Not the firſt of theſe: for the Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of Volition is preciſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>good</hi> or <hi>bonum,</hi> not <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priety;</hi> ſo that if we ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate them two, we ſhall find <hi>propriety</hi> to have no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:61142:25"/>of Eligibility in it; if there were, then there would be ſomething of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligibility too in our proper and perſonal evil as well as good. Nor is the ſecond true, that we cannot appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend anothers good. For it is moſt plain, that we can in our conception conjoyn pain or pleaſure, good or evil, with any other Soul or Mind, as well as our own; or we can ſuppoſe the ſame evil we ſuffer in another perſon. Who is there who hath himſelf felt the tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Stone, that doth
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:61142:25"/>not well underſtand the ſame in another, and pity him too when he hears him making grievous outcries, or giving other ſuch ſigns as he did himſelf, when he was under the ſame pain? Nay, though he was never in the ſame condition, yet he underſtands him to be affected with ſome great evil. It is true, ordinarily we do not apprehend one anothers evil ſo clearly as our own; but the reaſon is, becauſe the one is a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of Senſe, the other of Memory, or Imagination;
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:61142:26"/>the one is uſually a preſent Object, the other an abſent: and even our own abſent evil we apprehend not ſo well as our preſent. Final<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, all the pity and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion and friendſhip we ſee in the world, confutes both theſe pretences; eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially where our love to any perſon is great, which makes us to unite it to our ſelves (the firſt and eſſenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al property of love.) And conſider it but as a part of our ſelves, and ſometimes much the better (as it is in Wives and Children, and
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:61142:26"/>very dear friends) and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently to be the moſt truly and inwardly affected with the evil or good they ſuffer or enjoy. And thoſe happy Souls who have had clear and true apprehenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the moſt perfect and amiable Nature of God, have experienced, I doubt not, that they have infinite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly preferred the felicity of the Divine Nature before their own, his Will before theirs; and have thought and eſteemed themſelves not worthy of the leaſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard in compare with him;
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:61142:27"/>and which is ſtill moſt of all, could have been content to ſacrifice all Being and Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs to his pleaſure, if it were abſolutely neceſſary. And we ſee the ſame fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently amongſt Men one toward another, when a common Souldier, under an apprehenſion of the greater worth and bravery of his Commander, expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth his own life to certain danger, and deſtruction too, to ſave the others. In the next place, that there is an innate appetite in all men after this perfection of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neficence
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:61142:27"/>and doing good, without any ſelf-reſpect, I appeal to Univerſal Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience. Nor is there any man, who after he hath performed any ſuch act, is not pleaſed therewith, and ready to brag of it. It is true, the gratification of this Natural Appetite, or the poſſeſſion of ſuch a good, cannot but be delightful: but even this delight ſpring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing therefrom, may not be any thing of the End or Object foreſeen or propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, but only conſequent upon the action; as it is
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:61142:28"/>true it alſo may be. The pleaſure of doing good, may be one diſtinct part of the End and Effect of ones beneficence, as well as the good done to others, when one takes a view of ſome particular good things which conſtitute the whole End and Object.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, That this delight and pleaſure, from this per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of our Volition, or from Univerſal Benevo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, and in part conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent Beneficence, may be greater than from any other Object; and that there is
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:61142:28"/>a Capacity in our Souls to be more delighted there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with, than any other parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular good, methinks is hence moſt evidently pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, <hi>viz.</hi> Becauſe it is cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly the greateſt good we can poſſibly poſſeſs, (grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter than our own happineſs, as much as the whole Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe is greater than our<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves) and becauſe we are capable of ſeeing it to be ſo. Now certainly the Senſe and Perception of our actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al poſſeſſion of the greateſt good we are capable of; and that there neither is,
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:61142:29"/>nor can be any greater, muſt needs fill the Soul with the moſt complete intenſe ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying delight. It cannot be the Nature of the Soul to be pleaſed as much with thep oſſe ſſion of any other good, as with that which only ſhe ſees clearly to be abſolutely the greateſt ſhe or any other Being can ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain. It is plain therefore, that our duty and our in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt, our perfection and our happineſs are inſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, ſo long as God conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nues and preſerves our na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſuch as he hath made
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:61142:29"/>it: nor can we eaſily con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive it, if at all, to be other than it is.</p>
            <p n="14">14. After this, I ſcarce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly need mention ſo plain a conſequence, as that if Voli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion hath any leſs good for its Object than abſolutely the greateſt, it is a defect therein, of which there are indefinite degrees, till we come to the loweſt, which is mentioned before.</p>
            <p n="15">15. And it is this <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or relation of <hi>Volition &amp; actual and habitual inclination</hi> to their Object, which is called <hi>Moral Good &amp; Evil, Holineſs
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:61142:30"/>and Sin, bonum honeſtum &amp; inhoneſtum, Virtue and Vice,</hi> and by an hundred other Names, <hi>viz.</hi> When Voliti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on hath for its Object the greateſt good, (actually or habitually known, immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately or mediately) then is that Volition Morally good, honeſt, or virtuous: but when it hath any other leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer delectable good for its Object, (and ſome good it muſt have) then it is Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally Evil, or a Sin. Whence it appears, that Sin is a
<hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect</hi> only, or a <hi>Negation:</hi> for the Defect of this <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:61142:30"/>relation of Volition to its Object (which is always de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectable good) is only this, that it hath not for its Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject the greateſt good.</p>
            <p n="16">16. I have before juſt hint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, That this Moral Good is alſo a kind of <hi>bonum utile,</hi> or profitable good; that is to ſay, it is a means of, or hath in it ſome degree of Cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſality of delectable good. For Volition of any good, hath at leaſt a tendency to effect it, which is ſome degree of Cauſality; and in us it hath no more: like as the <hi>Niſus</hi> in Bodies to
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:61142:31"/>Motion is ſomething, and is a tendency which hath ſome degree of Cauſality of Motion in it; as appears from this, that if you re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move the impediment only, Motion preſently follows; and that there is plainly dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference between two Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, one of which hath, the other hath it not. But in God it always actually ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>effects it; and God by his power doth generally up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on occaſion of our Voliti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, make actually exiſtent delectable good, or thoſe things which cauſe it: and
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:61142:31"/>in this conſiſts all the good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Moral Good, or all its Eligibility, or that which makes it the Object of any Volition, or its per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection; for by <hi>perfection</hi> I mean <hi>bonum utile,</hi> or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable good, that which doth <hi>perficere</hi> or effect de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectable good. On the contrary, the evil of Sin, or that for which it is not eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gible, and refuſable, is the privation of a tendency to, or Cauſality of Delectable Good. Virtue therefore is a tendency to an infinite good, Sin a privation of it.</p>
            <pb n="58" facs="tcp:61142:32"/>
            <p n="17">17. Sin then is no ſmall or light thing, being in one reſpect plainly an infinite evil. For whereas our Voli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion may and ought to have for its Object an infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite Delectable Good, in reſpect of Extenſion, Inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and Duration, the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt Eternal Felicity of the Univerſe, and conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly tends to it, and hath ſome Cauſality thereof in it:</p>
            <p>When this our Volition is ſinful, or hath any leſſer good for its Object, there is a deprivation of all this.
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:61142:32"/>In this ſence that of the Schoolmen is true, <hi>That Sin is a Converſion of the Will from an Infinite Good to a Finite one.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="18">18. But this is not all: though the Evil or Miſchief of Sin immediately be
<hi>pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vative,</hi> yet often by neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary conſequence it is <hi>poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive</hi> alſo; as when one wills any Delectable Good to himſelf, which cannot be effected without the poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive inconvenience, grief, hurt, miſery of another. For example, if any one ſhould be of ſuch a temper,
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:61142:33"/>as to be delighted with a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nothers pain or ſuffering, and conſequently will and deſire it in order to that end, which is called pure Malice: Or if unlimited power to do what he liſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, and conſequently to do Miſchief (called Tyranny) pleaſe him; or if being pleaſed with Superiority and Eminency in any thing, (as in Power, Riches, Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, Happineſs,) in order to this his Superiority, he takes away from any perſon what he hath of all theſe; and theſe appetites may be
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:61142:33" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſo boundleſs, that they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be ſatisfyed but by an infinite miſchief. As if any Being, that he might be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finitely ſuperiour to all in happineſs, or in the poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of any good, ſhould not only take from all, all they poſſeſſed, but make all beſides himſelf the moſt extreamly miſerable. And there have been ſuch Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters among Men (ſome of the <hi>Roman</hi> Emperors, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers) who have advanced very far in this prodigious wickedneſs. Hiſtorians re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port <hi>Tiberius</hi> to have been
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:61142:34"/>ſo delighted with Cruelty, that he was termed <hi>Lutum ſanguine maceratum, a lump of Clay ſoaked in Blood;</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter which he more thirſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, than ſtrong drinks, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding that he lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved them ſo well, as to have the Name of <hi>Biberius Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dius Mero,</hi> inſtead of <hi>Tibe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius Claudius Nero.</hi> They tell us alſo, that
<hi>Caligula</hi> made it the diverſion of his Meals, to ſee men racked and Beheaded; and that
<hi>Nero</hi> ſet the City of <hi>Rome</hi> on fire, that he might have the glory of Re-building it,
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:61142:34"/>and having it called after his own Name, <hi>Neropolis.</hi> Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous certainly it is, to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin to lay aſide a certain tenderneſs of others good, and to be careleſs what miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief we do to any body, ſo we may gratifie our own Appetites. Though our power may be ſhort and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſufficient, yet our Minds may be ſoon debauched to ſuch a degree, as firſt to be content to moleſt or incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mode our Neighbour, then to ruine him, then to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do and deſtroy whole Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies, Cities, and Nations,
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:61142:35"/>for the ſake of ſome ſmall paltry pleaſure of our own; and at laſt to delight in it.</p>
            <p n="19">19. A ſecond perfection of Volition we have ſaid to be, in reſpect of the Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which is two fold. The firſt is Intenſion, Force, and Strength; of which it is certain there may be vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous degrees in the Actions of Spirits. The greateſt good, <hi>viz.</hi> That of the whole Univerſe, ought to have the greateſt ſtrength of Volition that can be, which is no leſs than Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite.
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:61142:35"/>And here is a neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary defect in all Finite Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional Beings whatſoever; only God, who is Infinite in Power, Force, Action, hath this; to his Nature alone it belongs; all other Beings fall infinitely ſhort of him; and therefore may be ſaid too to be faulty in compare with him. In the other perfection of our Volition, <hi>viz.</hi> the having its due Object an Infinite Good, God hath made us capable of being perfectly like him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf: but here the moſt perfect of his Creatures are
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:61142:36"/>at an infinite diſtance from him. The greateſt degree of this perfection, is to will the Univerſal good, or rather the greateſt good, with all the vehemency, zeal, and force, our Minds are capable of; and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trariwiſe, a great degree of the oppoſite defect, is to will the Univerſal good the moſt remiſly: but a greater degree, not to will it at all; and the greateſt of all, it ſeems both in reſpect of the Action and Object together, to will the leaſt good with the greateſt force and vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mency.
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:61142:36"/>Of this intenſion and firmneſs of our Voliti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and likewiſe our actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al and habitual inclination to the Univerſal good, the paſſions of deſire after, love to, and delight in ſo doing and being, are the cauſes and the effects too; and therefore ſigns, according to their reſpective degrees: and the being thus affected towards Piety, Charity, Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility, Spirituality, and all other inſtances thereof, is that which is ſignified by the phraſes of <hi>Virtues being na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural to us, it being the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per,
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:61142:37"/>Complexion, Conſtitution of our Minds; its being a li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving and vital principle, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducing fruits and effects of outward good actions.</hi> In the Scripture it is
<hi>the Spirit, li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving according to the Spirit, and being led by the Spirit, and delighting in the Law of God according to the inward man, and the new man crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted after God;</hi> becauſe the Object that pleaſeth is a Spiritual thing, and becauſe it is according to the Word of God dictated by the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of God, and from the influence or efficiency of
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:61142:37"/>Gods Spirit in us. Here may be noted, that the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree of the ſtrength of our Volition and inclination to the Univerſal good, and in order to that of our paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, ought at leaſt to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed that which is to any other particular good, or elſe it will be ineffectual. Whence it may be further uſefully obſerved, That they are not always to be deem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed or termed good men, who in Pulpit, Church, or private Converſation, not only appear, but really are very zealous and affectio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:61142:38"/>in Religion; becauſe they generally are of paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onate Tempers in other matters, and may perhaps have greater affections, and conſequently inclinations to other Objects. A man of a more calm and ſedate temper in Religion, provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded that the greateſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree of affection he hath be directed to his duty, may be a good man; when one of a more boiſterous and paſſionate one, whatever he is vulgarly taken for, may be indeed a bad man. The one ſhall more ſteadily and
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:61142:38"/>conſtantly do his duty than the other. In like manner, when a man ſins delibe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rately, it is a ſign of a grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter bent, ſtrength, and inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the inclination of the Will to its undue Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, and of a leſs to Virtue; when he ſins by ſurprize, or on a ſudden, it is not ſo much a ſign thereof. But theſe and many other things uſually treated of in Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rality, may with a little conſideration be eaſily and diſtinctly determined from the foregoing Concluſions, and a wary obſervation and
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:61142:39"/>experience of the operati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of our Minds.</p>
            <p n="20">20. The ſecond Perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of our Volition and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clination, in reſpect of the
<hi>Action,</hi> is Conſtancy, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance, or Duration. So that in this reſpect, the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt degree is to have the Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lition and Inclination <hi>perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually</hi> and
<hi>eternally</hi> directed to the abſolutely greateſt good; the loweſt, to have them ſo directed but for one moment, or the leaſt of time. This perfection of the <hi>Action of Volition,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs only to God, who
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:61142:39"/>always actually ſo wills: (for he is always the ſame without any change) but of <hi>habitual inclination,</hi> may be in us and other rational Creatures. So that there are only theſe three gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral perfections of Virtue. The firſt, the direction of Volition and Inclination to their right Object; the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, that they be with the greateſt force or ſtrength any Nature is capable of; the third, that they be the moſt perpetual and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant, or continued and laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; or in three words,
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:61142:40"/>Sincerity, Generoſity, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancy.</p>
            <p n="21">21. And yet there ſeems to be another perfection of Volition in reſpect of the Action; and that is, the juſt moderation of it to the various parts of this U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niverſal good:
<hi>i. e.</hi> When we will any part thereof knowingly, to will it more or leſs in due proportion to the ſhare of goodneſs that is in it, compared with ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther part; and the defect contrariwiſe will be, to will a leſs good more than a grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; and the greateſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:61142:40"/>is, when we will the leaſt part more than all the reſt; for example, a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the leaſt pleaſure to our ſelves, before the Eternal Felicity of God and all the world beſides. And this may be, not only when any two parts are inconſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent one with another, as when I will to gratifie my ſelf in that which diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth God, and is miſchievous or hurtful to my Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour; but alſo when they are conſiſtent, nay, conjoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed together, and they are altogether the Object of
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:61142:41"/>my Will. Thus if a man builds an Hoſpital, or gives any Alms to the Poor, he knows this action will pleaſe God, benefit others, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure himſelf Reputation; and he doth it for all theſe reaſons; he wills all this good together as one: but here that of theſe which he may moſt will, that which he chiefly intends, is his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation, and his own plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure therefrom, which ought to be poſſibly with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out compare the leaſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garded, though ſomewhat. But in truth, this is but a
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:61142:41"/>ſign of that perfection and <hi>defect</hi> of Volition, which is in reſpect of the Object or of the Action. For if a man wills only his own good, or only to pleaſe God, excluſively one to the other, the defect ſeems to be in not having the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal good, but ſome par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular good for the Object of his Volition, becauſe both and more ſhould be taken together: But if a man wills one good compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed of more parts, and wills that part moſt which in truth is the leaſt good, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:61142:42"/>he doth it knowingly, or ignorantly: if knowing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, (which is moſt frequent, whatever pretences men may make) then the defect is in not willing the greateſt good; and conſequently, it is a defect in reſpect of the Object before-mentioned; for he cannot but know, that it tends to a leſſer Good, to will a leſſer more than a greater. If igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantly and erroneouſly, judging that the greater Good, which is indeed the leſſer, the ignorance is either through ſome <hi>preſent</hi> defect
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:61142:42"/>in the actual Volition, or habitual inclination to the Univerſal good, ones
<hi>Duty, Right, Honeſt;</hi> or it is not: if it be, it is plain where and what the defect is,
<hi>viz.</hi> in the Action or Inclination before-mentioned; if it be not, then there is no defect in the preſent Volition at all, (whatever may have been in former Actions of the Will, by which ſuch ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance may be contract<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed) but only in the Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding; the Volition may have for all that its due Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, <hi>viz.</hi> the greateſt good.</p>
            <p n="22">
               <pb n="80" facs="tcp:61142:43"/> 22. From theſe propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions it follows, that the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of this defect of Voli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or of <hi>Sin,</hi> depends not upon any Law, or upon a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Beings Will whatſoever, (though its exiſtence doth, becauſe it being only a <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or relation, it cannot exiſt actually, unleſs the ſubject thereof do, namely ſome <hi>Will</hi> or other:) but though we ſuppoſe no other Being in the World beſides one, and no antecedent Will, yet theſe which have been be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore-mentioned, would be perfections and defects
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:61142:43"/>whenſoever it exiſts. It is true, that Laws may be the ſigns of what is juſt and unjuſt, right and wrong; but not the efficient cauſes, any otherwiſe than a Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject is the efficient cauſe of the exiſtence of its proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, as is but now ſaid. Theſe Laws alſo are ſometimes ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary &amp; inſeparable ſigns, ſometimes in ſeveral degrees contingent and probable only, according to the knowledge and juſtice of the Law-maker. Thoſe which are certainly Laws of God, who is infallibly wiſe,
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:61142:44"/>and immutably juſt, are moſt inſeparable and cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain ſigns of what is juſt and right: but thoſe which are any other Creatures, are more or leſs probable ones. Laws do not make, but ſuppoſe the thing juſt which they command. It is true alſo what the Apoſtle St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>That where there is no Law, there is no tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion;</hi> becauſe God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf and his Volition of what is right and juſt are eternal: or the Apoſtle may mean by <hi>Law,</hi> not ſtrictly an act of ſome
<hi>Will</hi>
               <pb n="83" facs="tcp:61142:44"/>concerning anothers <hi>Action and Will,</hi> but an obligati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to
<hi>will</hi> or do any thing; a <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. Such there always is, whenever any will exiſt, being a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation betwen the <hi>Will</hi> and its due Object the Univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal good. Beſides, St. <hi>Paul</hi> may mean comparatively; the Tranſgreſſion or Sin is much leſs, where there is no expreſs known Law.</p>
            <p n="23">23. Nor doth the nature of Sin or Virtue depend upon <hi>liberum arbitrium,</hi> or
<hi>Free-will;</hi> for whether any <hi>Will</hi> hath power to deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:61142:45"/>its own Volition to the greateſt, or any leſſer good or no; (which I do not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny) yet moſt certainly, whenever there is a directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thereof to a leſſer good, there is a defect in that Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lition, come it from what cauſe it will; though it ſhould be the effect of ſome other Being without it, which by his power was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſo to determine it; or ſuppoſe any Nature ſhould be eternally and neceſſarily ſo conſtituted.</p>
            <p n="24">24. It follows likewiſe, that ſuppoſing it poſſible for
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:61142:45"/>any Being to have for the Object of his Volition the <hi>rectitude</hi> the
<hi>perfection</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, and ſhould not place it in the <hi>willing the greateſt good,</hi> but in willing ſome particular, or (which is moſt common) ſome perſonal good, as ſelf-preſervation; this very Volition would have that defect in it we call Sin, and would not be capable of any reward, <hi>i. e.</hi> any thing which ſhould maintain or encourage ſuch an action. If it were poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible for a man unfeignedly in his Conſcience to judge
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:61142:46"/>it his bounden duty to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire and purſue always as his ultimate end, his own greateſt perſonal good, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out regard to God or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and accordingly ſhould Will and Act; this would be a vitious man. And whether God may not by way of puniſhment for pride,
<hi>&amp;c.</hi> permit a man ſo to err, is not here to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined: and there have been two pernicious and fooliſh miſtakes, if not wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Errors, that men might ſecurely indulge their luſts, of ſome late new Modellers
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:61142:46"/>of Morality; to which a great part of the ill-nature and debauchery of the Age is to be imputed: the one, the advancing of their per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonal good, to the place and dignity of the laſt end of all their actions; the other, the pitching upon no bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter than the preſervation of life and limb, or (to enlarge their own Sence) the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt meaſures of the Conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niencies, Comforts, and Pleaſures proper to this bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily life. In theſe Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons they have quite perver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the nature of things,
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:61142:47"/>and made Vice to be Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue. Or becauſe, according to the ſame mens Doctrine, every one is neceſſarily car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried to his own greateſt good or happineſs in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, only through ignorance is oft out of the way, they have made no Vice at all, ſubſtituting in its room Fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and Imprudence.</p>
            <p n="25">25. What hath been ſaid of <hi>Volition,</hi> may be ſaid of <hi>Actual and Habitual In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clination;</hi> and becauſe Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lition and Actual Inclinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on are but ſometimes exi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtent in men, but Habitual
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:61142:47"/>Inclinations conſtant and perpetual; 'tis according to this a man is chiefly to be eſtimated, <hi>viz.</hi> by three things. (1.) Its direction to its right Object, the U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niverſal Good. (2.) The force and ſtrength thereof. (3.) Its conſtancy or fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quency in the Soul: each of which hath degrees; ſo that it is eaſie to ſet down cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain rules for the judgment of the goodneſs or badneſs of any man. For example ſake only: He is the worſt man in the firſt reſpect, who is habitually inclined to, and
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:61142:48"/>in love with the meaneſt or leaſt delectable good; in the ſecond reſpect, who is the moſt vehemently inclined thereto; in the third reſpect, who is perpetually or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly ſo. Contrariwiſe, he is the beſt, who hath the greateſt good abſolutely, or the <hi>Eternal Felicity</hi> (for by Felicity I mean the greateſt degree of delight or plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure as to intenſion) <hi>of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſe,</hi> or all Beings ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſtent for the Object of his Habitual Inclination; or who is habitually inclined thereto, and that with the
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:61142:48"/>greateſt force and ſtrength of his nature, and then con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly and perpetually. It is eaſie to ſee, what an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>definite number of degrees there are between theſe two extremes, in all the three reſpects. The greateſt dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulty is not to know theſe Rules of our Judgment; but to know our ſelves, and conſequently to apply them. And ſince <hi>Denominatio fit à Majore,</hi> he only is to be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led a <hi>good man,</hi> who hath a ſtronger and more conſtant Habitual Inclination to the Univerſal good, than to any
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:61142:49"/>one or more particulars. And this was, or might have been, the reaſon why Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrdome was ſo highly e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteemed and magnified in the Primitiue Church. A Martyr by his ſuffering for his Faith, even though he was not actually Baptized, was thought to expiate all former bad life, and to be undoubtedly ſaved, or to obtain a moſt glorious and bliſsful condition in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven: becauſe ſuch his ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring death, or parting with life itſelf, deemed the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt <hi>perſonal good</hi> amongſt
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:61142:49"/>men, rather than to deny that Truth which they ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed God had commanded to believe and profeſs, and conſequently to diſobey God, was a certain ſign and argument of a ſtronger actual and habitual inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion at that time of his death to obey God, and conſequently to that which was <hi>right, juſt,</hi> and <hi>good,</hi> than to any other thing in the world beſides. Nor may it be here amiſs, to hint how eaſie it is to underſtand it poſſible for this Habitual Inclination, Bent, and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſion
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:61142:50"/>to any certain Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, to be ſo forcible and ſtrong, as to be inconſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent with an act of Free Will or choice about that Object: nor may a man be able to divert, ſuſpend, or withhold his actual Voliti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, conſent, or embrace from it when it is propoſed. Though by prudent contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance, theſe Habitual Incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations generally, (I do not ſay all) may alſo by degrees be weakned, and at laſt quite extinguiſhed and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed.</p>
            <p n="26">26. 'Tis as eaſie hence
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:61142:50"/>to deduce all particular vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues and vices, of which we ſhall find many to have as yet no Names. For one way, and the moſt common, is by diſtinguiſhing particular delectable Good or Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure (whether that particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Good be in a mans ſelf, or in another as the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject; whether it be mine or anothers; but it is uſual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, if not always, a mans own) from its various Cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes or Objects. And it ſeems there may be ſix ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral ones (I do but now ſuggeſt, not determine.)
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:61142:51"/>(1) The poſſeſſion of any Good in general ſo eſteem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; many things thus one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly pleaſe. (2) The pain, miſchief, evil ſuffering of another: Whether any Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing is of ſuch a temper as to be delighted therewith, let others conſider; but I ſee no reaſon why it is not poſſible. Now to will ones delight or pleaſure from this Object or Cauſe, is called <hi>Malice;</hi> to be habitually in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clined thereto, <hi>Maliciouſneſs:</hi> but the renouncing of this, or the nolition of it, or the volition of its abſence, and
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:61142:51"/>inſtead thereof the volition of the univerſal Good, may be called
<hi>Charity,</hi> or if there be any fitter Name. (3) The third Object cauſing delight to us, is power to do what one pleaſeth, to make any thing conſequent upon ones will; of which three de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees; Liberty, Equality, Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periority. Now to have pleaſure ariſing from hence, the onely Object of our volition, is an action of <hi>pride;</hi> the onely Object of our habitual inclination, the vice thereof: To refuſe it, as before, or will its abſence,
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:61142:52"/>is <hi>Humility.</hi> (4) Mere A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctivity and Life, and that exerted in all the operati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of our Souls; ſuch as is, for example, mere Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templation and Knowledge, Senſe, Imagination, ſtrong Paſſions, intenſe Volitions or Reſolutions. And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe Knowledge may be indefinitely divided accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to its Objects, here a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone may be almoſt an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite number of particular Vices and Virtues. This Vice and contrary Virtue have no names, ſome kinds of it may. (5) Some cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:61142:52"/>agreeable corporeal Motions, or Motions of our Bodies, to which our Souls are united, <hi>ſuaves Corporis Commotiones,</hi> as ſome have called them, which I know no common name to ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie them by, unleſs <hi>Titilla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> may be allowed. Theſe (as
<hi>Cartes</hi> thinks) create pleaſure to the mind, as a natural ſign of the health or good conſtitution of the Body: and the pleaſures ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing in the Soul from them, <hi>Plato</hi> calls <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, Pleaſures which are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veyed
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:61142:53"/>to the Soul by the Body. Of this ſort are all Senſations; amongſt which are thoſe of Health, Calm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and Serenity; other bodily tempers; many cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poreal paſſions, ſuch as Love, Joy, Hope, Acquieſcence, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Nay, I may ſay all per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps; for it may be that ſome Souls may be deligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with the corporeal paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of Sadneſs and Grief; though in theſe not onely the Mechanical or Corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>real Vibrations and motions of Fibres, Nerves, and Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, delight and pleaſe;
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:61142:53"/>but alſo the Senſe, Perce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption, Life, and ſome kind of action of the Soul. So that this pleaſure is mixed from two very different Objects; one Corporeal, t'other In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tellectual: and indeed, moſt of our pleaſure or delight ariſeth from ſeveral Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects mixed and blended to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether. Now to have the pleaſure or delight ariſing from ſuch motions of our Bodies, the entire Object of our Volition, is an act of <hi>Senſuality;</hi> and to be habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually enclined thereto, the Vice: But to refuſe this
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:61142:54"/>Self-pleaſure, or to will its abſence, is <hi>Sobriety</hi> or
<hi>Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perance,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. (6) The perfection of a mans na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, of all his Faculties, (which may be referred to the firſt) and amongſt the reſt, the <hi>Rectitude, Honeſty, Probity</hi> of his Actions and Inclinations, or his Virtue, may be and is the cauſe of great pleaſure and delight to him. Now even to have this delight; (uſually cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the ſatisfaction of a good Conſcience) nay let me adde, that pleaſure which ariſeth from hopes and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurance
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:61142:54"/>of a reward, and from the poſſeſſion of it too: I ſay, to have this the entire Object of our Voli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, Intention, Inclination, or in greater proportion to other parts of the Univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal Good than it ought, is a ſin and vice which wants a name, as doth its oppoſite Virtue. Finally, (not to inſiſt upon this diſtribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion I have made, which I brought onely for example of ſome general Heads) as many as there are Objects which may pleaſe or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light us, and conſequently
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:61142:55"/>correſpondent Appetites, (which are numberleſs:) So many ſorts of ſins or vices may there be; they all may be reduced to ſome ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral heads, and thoſe heads divided, and theſe again ſubdivided, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="27">27. Many other diſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butions of Virtue and Vice may be made; as from the parts of the Univerſal Good diſtinguiſhed by its Subjects, uſually comprehended un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der three, <hi>viz. God,</hi> All created or finite Beings be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides our ſelves, under the name of our
<hi>Neighbour,</hi>
               <pb n="105" facs="tcp:61142:55"/>(though we know little of any other, or what we can do to or for them beſides Mankind) and laſtly <hi>our ſelves.</hi> The Volition of the Univerſal Good, our laſt end, therefore may be reſolved into three parts, <hi>viz.</hi> The love of God; The love of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ur Neighbour; The love of our ſelves: Or, Piety, Charity, and pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent and ſober care of our own greateſt concerns. And by Love, I mean not Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude, but a Volition of the good of the Object be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved, whether the good
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:61142:56"/>be an abſent or preſent good. To will an abſent good, and deſire it for the perſon we love, can onely take place with reſpect to our Neighbour and our ſelves, not to God, who we know cannot want any thing: But to will a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent good, may be to God alſo. We may will, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove, rejoyce, delight in the infinite perfection and happineſs of his nature, which he always doth and cannot but poſſeſs.</p>
            <p n="28">28. But theſe three parts of the Univerſal Good are
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:61142:56"/>always to be intended <hi>to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether</hi> actually or habitual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, although but one of them may be firſt regarded. As when we <hi>actually</hi> will any good to our Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, we ought at leaſt <hi>ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitually</hi> to will it, not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly becauſe thereby we do good to him, but alſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it pleaſeth God, and it is our own perfection, and will be for our own greater good ſo to do; al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though that we firſt looked at was our Neighbours good. And theſe three parts are ſo neceſſarily and
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:61142:57"/>inſeparably conjoyned, that we may and ought always <hi>habitually</hi> to believe, when we endeavour to effect the one, the other will neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily follow. Thus, for ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, to love God, the Volition of good to him, or the rejoycing in the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection and happineſs of his Nature, hath neceſſarily conſequent others and our own Good: Becauſe all the happineſs of Creatures depends thereon, and flows therefrom, (from his <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> and from his moſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Nature;) and becauſe
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:61142:57"/>it is and will be our grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt Perfection, Comfort, Reward. So again, if we ſincerely love and do good to our Neighbour, we may be ſure it pleaſeth God, and is beſt for our ſelves. And ſo Laſtly, our own greateſt good truly as to Intenſion, Extenſion, and Duration; or our greateſt perfection and happineſs, is in and by loving of God, and doing all the good we can to our Neighbour.</p>
            <p n="29">29. It may be further obſerved, that all actions and correſpondent habits
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:61142:58"/>of the <hi>Will</hi> whatſoever, which do effect the Univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal good, have been uſed to be called Virtues, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any conſideration of the <hi>end</hi> of the Action, or the <hi>ultimate Object</hi> thereof; and for diſtinction-ſake may be called
<hi>inſtrumental</hi> or <hi>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventual</hi> vertues: The o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſort of Volitions which have their due end, or due ultimate Object conſidered as ſuch, having the name of <hi>principal</hi> or <hi>inherent</hi> Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues. So, for example, to apply the mind to attention and conſideration, purſuit
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:61142:58"/>after or love of the Truth, [<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>] are accounted Virtues, becauſe they uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally are the cauſes of good effects in the world more than hurtful ones. Such a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain are to judge rightly and truly, eſpecially con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning other men; <hi>i.e.</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways onely according to what really appears to us from things themſelves, not becauſe we imagine ſo: Although the end of theſe actions may be no other than the pleaſure and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light a man takes in ſuch conduct of himſelf in ſuch
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:61142:59"/>temper and actions, or ſome perſonal and proper good, and therefore indeed are inherently vitious, according to our ſenſe of Virtue and Vice. So likewiſe
<hi>Libera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity,</hi> or the diſtribution of many good things to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, conſidered without its end; I mean, the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Volition of ſo do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, or the action of the Will, of which the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward bodily action is a Signe and Effect onely, and belongs not to this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent diſcourſe.</p>
            <p n="30">
               <pb n="113" facs="tcp:61142:59"/> 30. And 'tis here only, that it is generally true, that <hi>Virtus conſiſtit in medio, i.e.</hi> there may be too much or too little of ſuch actions and habits, both which ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremes do not effect the U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niverſal good, but are of more ill than good conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence. Thus, for example, A man may attend too much ſometimes and to ſome things, or too little; he may give too much or too little, the firſt of which is called
<hi>prodigality,</hi> the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond <hi>parſimony</hi> or cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſs. But it is falſe and
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:61142:60"/>abſurd to ſay this of <hi>Virtue</hi> as it is before defined; for there can be no exceſs there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in. Nay, ſome of theſe very actions may have no exceſs; as Juſtice rightly deſined, and Faith.</p>
            <p n="31">31. Thoſe of this ſort of actions and habits are called Virtues, which are obſerved and believed to have more good effects than evil ones in the total ſum. Inſomuch that if they have very few more good than bad conſequences, they are termed mean Virtues, as
<hi>Frugality;</hi> if very many
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:61142:60"/>and great ones, then they are called great Virtues, ſuch as
<hi>Juſtice,</hi> or giving to every one his due, <hi>i.e.</hi> that to each particular, (and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently to ones ſelf alſo) as to quality, quantity, time, and all other reſpects of gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving it, which is moſt for the Univerſal good; <hi>Meek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> [<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,] or ſlowneſs to be moved to anger, or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turning evil when provo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked by infirmities, ill acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, or injuries to our ſelves or others; <hi>Clemency,</hi> or an omiſſion of part of puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; <hi>Forbearance</hi> and long
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:61142:61"/>ſufferance, [<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>] a delay of puniſhment, or of returning evil for a long time after many injuries; <hi>Forgiveneſs,</hi> or an omiſſion to puniſh, or return any evil for injuries at all; <hi>Bounty, Courage, Veracity, conſent to the Conſtitution and Adminiſtration of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> or entring into a So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety, where ſome may be on purpoſe ſet apart and appointed for finding out and improving and ſecuring what is for the common be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit of that Society, and particularly for the arbitra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:61142:61"/>of all differences, which the <hi>Jews</hi> call <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>Judges or Government:</hi> and make it one of the ſeven Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts of the Sons of
<hi>Noah,</hi> or of thoſe whoſe advanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of benefit to Mankind were ſo eaſily and well known, that all men who had the uſe of Reaſon and Natural light only, allowed and commanded them. But there is no greater inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental or eventual Virtue than <hi>Chriſtian Faith,</hi> or to be a Believer; by which I mean, Obedience to <hi>Jeſus</hi> in Gods Name, which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:61142:62"/>of, or contains two things. (1.) An aſſent to all things <hi>Jeſus,</hi> or thoſe commiſſionated and inſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by him, taught and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered, as infallibly true. And (2.) A practiſing all he hath commanded. Bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter words than theſe we have not to expreſs theſe two particulars by, though both indeed are doing and practiſing commands. For the precepts of Chriſtian Faith contain the moſt ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere, and generous, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant inherent Virtue; as alſo the greateſt inſtrumen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:61142:62"/>or eventual ones. The very firſt part alone, or <hi>Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent,</hi> is generally in various degrees a great inſtrumen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal Virtue. Some habits a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain there are, whoſe ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage of good or bad effects is ſo uncertain, that it is diſputed whether they be Virtues or not. Some at ſome times ſay they are, and others ſay not. For example,
<hi>Facetiouſneſs</hi> and <hi>Taciturni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.</hi> And for the ſame rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, it is hardly yet deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined, or determinable, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſome diſpoſitions and actions be Vices, or Vitious
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:61142:63"/>or no; <hi>viz.</hi> becauſe the advantage or exceſs of good or bad conſequences of ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſide is yet unknown. Such perhaps may be <hi>Scru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puloſity,</hi> or an aptitude to examine the lawfulneſs of every the ſmalleſt action; not in reſpect of the end on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, (for that is eaſily known) but of the effect, which is moſtly difficult, often im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible to know. So alſo Separation from ſome par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular corrupted Church. Some may think Separation, ſome Communion the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt miſchief. Such indivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dual
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:61142:63"/>actions alſo may be called <hi>indifferent.</hi> Theſe for their very being ſuch, are not by any man to be done at all; and a man is always to do that which is not
<hi>indifferent,</hi> or to act be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he judgeth upon ſo much conſideration as is fit to be allowed or ſufficient for things of no more im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portance, that of his acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on there may be more good than bad conſequences, and more good conſequences than of his omiſſion of it, or doing any other action at that time. Thoſe acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:61142:64"/>alſo are by ſome term<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>indifferent,</hi> which though they are at one time in ſome circumſtances of beſt effect, and therefore to be done; yet in others 'tis confeſſed they are not. If ſo, there may be a great many degrees of Indifferen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy. Some actions may be more, ſome leſs <hi>indifferent</hi> than others, in reſpect of frequency and number of conveniencies or good ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects. Some may be for the moſt part of many and great good conſequences and ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects, but ſeldom of any
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:61142:64"/>hurtful ones, and thoſe but ſmall and few. On the contrary, ſome may more <hi>generally</hi> be very inconveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent and noxious, yet ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times convenient and uſeful. Some laſtly may be near e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qual. All which hindereth not, but that every one of theſe individual actions, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording as with all their cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances they are judged to be of moſt good or bad conſequences, are as much to be done or not to be done <hi>at that particular time,</hi> as if they were of that ſort of actions which were per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petually
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:61142:65"/>to be done or ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtained from. And theſe are the things generally a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout which the World with an unproportionate confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence diſſent and quarrel, and contend unto wounds and death itſelf.</p>
            <p n="32">32. Many other are the uſeful inferences which may be made from theſe few Obſervations, and many the Queſtions determined thereby. As only for in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance ſake: It is an ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Queſtion among the Writers of Ethicks, and it may be of ſome impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance,
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:61142:65"/>whether <hi>Virtutes ſunt connexae, all Virtues are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nected?</hi> ſo that if there be one in any Subject, there are all. To which it is eaſily anſwered, that they are not. For it is plain, that a man may have a more ſtrong and prevailing habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual inclination to his <hi>duty,</hi> to that which is <hi>juſt and right,</hi> to pleaſe and obey God, to the Univerſal good, than to ſome one or more certain Objects, but not than to ſome other. So ſome men eſpecially, if ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanced in years, may prefer
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:61142:66"/>their duty and acting ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to Conſcience, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore any ſenſual pleaſures; but not before Riches, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation, Dignity, Power, Self-will, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> They may have ſo little inclination to the former, as eaſily to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject it to their Conſcience; but ſo violent and impetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to the latter, that they are not to be governed or commanded by their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, or a judgement of, and habitual inclination to their duty. They may be, as is uſually ſaid, perhaps, Covetous, Vain-glorious,
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:61142:66"/>Ambitious, Proud, and Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinate; but not Voluptuous: and on the contrary, (to ſpeak in the received ſtyle) ſome may be very inſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of Glory or Greatneſs, but furiouſly carried to the pleaſures of Senſe. And hence it appears, that the Characters which Hiſtori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans have given of ſome men, may be true, namely, that there was in them
<hi>Magnae Virtutes, nec minora Vitia;</hi> great Virtues, and as great Vices. But it is as plain, that it is an ordinary miſtake of ſome perſons, who ſay,
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:61142:67"/>that every man hath the ſeeds and roots of all par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Vices in his nature; if by thoſe words they mean, an <hi>inordinate and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moderate habitual inclination or appetite.</hi> And I know not what they can mean elſe, unleſs it be a bare capacity; but then there would be the ſeeds of all Virtues as well as Vices. For there may be ſo many ſins as there are Appetites, and ſo many Appetites as there are Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects: and there are ſome objects from which the Souls of ſome men have a
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:61142:67"/>natural averſion; and this is to be underſtood, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of individual objects, but alſo of ſome kinds of them, and conſequently of ſome kinds of ſins.</p>
            <p n="33">33. But it is a Queſtion of much greater conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, what Virtues and Vices are the greateſt, and who are the moſt Virtuous or Vicious perſons? For according to our right in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation and judgement herein, our Opinions and Actions, our Inclinations and Behaviour, our Rewards and Puniſhments towards
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:61142:68"/>men, ought principally to be directed and governed. Now Vices or Sins (to take only that part) are to be eſtimated either according to their <hi>principle</hi> and
<hi>end,</hi> or according to their <hi>effect</hi> and <hi>conſequence:</hi> or they are either
<hi>inherent</hi> or <hi>eventual,</hi> as hath been before ſaid. In reſpect of the principle or end, there is no one kind or ſort of ſin univerſally grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter than another; for there may be as great an exceſs of <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or ſelf-love, in one ſort as in another; and that is the greateſt ſin in
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:61142:68"/>this reſpect, in which there is a greater exceſs of <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or habitual inclination to ones proper and perſonal good, above Univerſal Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, or above the habitual inclination to the Univerſal good. Thus there may be as great exceſs of
<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> in <hi>ſenſuality,</hi> as in <hi>pride</hi> or <hi>ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice.</hi> I ſay it may be ſo, though more generally it is reaſonably believed and ſuppoſed that there is more in theſe two laſt; and that becauſe there are uſually more and greater miſchie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous effects to others viſible
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:61142:69"/>and known to him that is guilty of them, than in the firſt: whence one muſt needs have a leſs regard to the good of others compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with his own, than the other. But in reſpect of the effect or conſequence, there is always a great dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference between the kinds of ſins, and one is much worſe than another. Thus <hi>Malice</hi> and <hi>Ambition</hi> are much greater ſins than <hi>Vain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glory</hi> or <hi>Senſuality,</hi> eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſome kinds of it, ſuch as the immoderate love of Bodily Exerciſes, Divertiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:61142:69"/>and Paſtimes. In particular, or rather indivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dual ſins or ill actions, there may be always difference both in reſpect of the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple and the effect. So a particular ſin of Malice, &amp; Spight, and Revenge, may be much greater and more heinous than a ſin of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temperance or Fornication, both in reſpect of <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or ſelf-love, in oppoſition to the good of others, and in reſpect of the hurtful and noxious effects and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequences. Sometimes a particular ſin may be grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:61142:70"/>in reſpect of the effect than another, but not in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of the principle. Thus one act of Pride or Malice in any man, may have ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny more miſchievous conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences upon it than an act of Intemperance or For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication; but yet there may be leſs of the exceſs of <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> in that than in this; the man perhaps being ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant of many of the ill Conſequences thereof, whereas in this he ſaw them and yet committed the ſin. We ought to diſtinguiſh between the greatneſs of a
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:61142:70"/>
               <hi>ſin</hi> and of a <hi>ſinner.</hi> He is not always in Gods account (who knows the inclinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the Soul certainly) the greateſt ſinner, who commits the greateſt ſin. I mean, he is not always the moſt guilty of an <hi>inherent</hi> ſin, who is the moſt guilty of the greateſt <hi>eventual</hi> ſin: and on the contrary, one man may be
<hi>inherently,</hi> or in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of the principle, more ſinful and vicious in the commiſſion of a leſs <hi>even<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual</hi> ſin, than another in the commiſſion of a grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. Thus oft-times he
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:61142:71"/>may be a worſe man, or a greater ſinner <hi>inherently,</hi> who is guilty of Vain-glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, (which ſeems to have ſo few more evil than good conſequences upon it, and therefore to be a leſs <hi>Even<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual</hi> ſin than Fornication or Intemperance) than he who is guilty of Fornication or Intemperance.</p>
            <p n="34">34. So likewiſe it hath been diſputed, whether a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctual inclinations and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſions, or (as ſome call them) appetites to ſin, concupiſcences without con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of the Will, or actual
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:61142:71"/>Volition, be ſinful? To which it is to be anſwered, that it is plain they are ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful. But withal, that the Wills not conſenting, or rather the actual nilling and refuſing them becauſe they are ſinful, is a certain ſign of the Superiority or Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valency juſt at that time of its habitual inclination to that which is right and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt; as the not regarding at all, and not attending whether they be ſinful, and not checking them if they ſeem ſo to be, is a ſign of the contrary. For there
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:61142:72"/>may be not onely divers, but contrary habitual incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations in the Soul at the ſame time. But as for mere thoughts or ſuggeſtions of what is ſinful or unlawful, as of Revenge, or Luſt, or Vain-glory, there can be no ſin in them; And when they are aſſentedto, or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighted in, the ſin is not in thoſe thoughts, but in the actual Volition or Inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Will. It is not a ſin, for example, for a man to have ſuch a thought as this:
<hi>Miſchief thou ſuch a man becauſe he once miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chieved
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:61142:72"/>you: Do ſuch a thing, becauſe ſuch perſons will ſpeak well of and applaud you for ſuch a performance:</hi> For ſuch a thought is but an Object of my Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, and propoſed to my Will perhaps; it is not in my Will, in which one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly is ſin. If it were a ſin barely to have ſuch a thought, then it would be ſo if I had it conveyed to me by reading or hearing of ſuch words; which no man can think. Neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, the emerging or ſpring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of ſuch thoughts from
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:61142:73"/>our ſelves, is a very proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſign of habitual ſinful inclinations in us. For it is a ſign (though not a ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary one) of ſome cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poreal Paſſion of Love, or Delight, or Deſire, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyned to ſuch Thoughts and Objects; or of ſome ſuch bodily diſpoſition, and perhaps mental temper, which naturally impreſſeth or cauſeth ſuch inclinations. The ſpontaneous emergen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of certain thoughts in us, uſually proceeds from ſuch a diſpoſition of the Body in us, as is the cauſe
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:61142:73"/>of delight and love to ſuch Objects; and then thoſe paſſions (if not hindered) impreſs on the Will actual and habitual inclinations. What is meant by ſin, and ſinful, hath been before laid down, <hi>viz.</hi> when the Incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation and Volition of the Will hath for its Object on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſome Particular good, and not the Univerſal (or that which God hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded by Revelation or Reaſon, that which plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth him, which is all one; becauſe the Commands of God are, and are by all
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:61142:74"/>men taken to be an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeparable ſign thereof) actually or habitually;
<hi>i. e. actually</hi> perceived, or <hi>habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually</hi> and <hi>confuſedly</hi> remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred. For it is of great moment to be obſerved, that when the Underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding actually takes notice of and regards, and the Will is carried to ſome par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular good only, ſuch as is ones daily food, ſleep, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> yet the Will may by an ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitual memory be carried to, or have for its object the Univerſal good, and that which is right, juſt, honeſt:
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:61142:74"/>for the Underſtanding may have concluded <hi>generally</hi> from Revelation, or Reaſon, or the common uncontra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicted practice of the world, that my particular uſe and enjoyment in ſuch meaſure and ſeaſons of ſuch particular good things, is in ſuch circumſtances for the univerſal good; that it en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ables me to do more good, and conſequently to pleaſe God and better my own condition: and the Will may act upon ſuch an habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Memory, without any actual perception prece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding.
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:61142:75"/>'Tis much like a mans <hi>habitual</hi> direction of all his ſteps to the end of his journey, though he doth not in every ſtep, nay per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps in very few, <hi>actually</hi> think thereof. And as it is a certain ſign of this habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual direction, that the man attends and is ſagacious as much as the danger of go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out of the way requires; and that if he hath by ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers admonition, or any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther means, any ſuſpicion that he is out of the way, he preſently ſtops and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires, and endeavours to
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:61142:75"/>be ſatisfied whether he be in the right way or no: So it is alſo a ſign of the <hi>habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual</hi> inclination of the Will to that which is right, which is for the Univerſal good, (of which the indubitable commands of God are a certain mark) if in any ſuch ordinary and common acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of life he be as wary and circumſpect as the dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger and the importance, compared with other mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and the likelihood of his erring, requires: and when he hath any ſufficient reaſon to ſuſpect he doth or
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:61142:76"/>may err, to ſtop, to abſtain, to conſider. And this is all I have at preſent to return you in Anſwer to your firſt Queſtion.</p>
            <p n="35">35. I have (Sir) in theſe Propoſitions made uſe of Scholaſtick terms, or ſuch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like, which I know are not much agreeable to the hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour of this Age: but in truth I could not avoid it; oft-times in the moſt recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved ſtyle either there wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Words, as far as I know, or they being of confuſed, looſe, and uncertain ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, ſometimes ſignify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:61142:76"/>one thing, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times another; ſometimes more or leſs (as every one may inform themſelves) they would not ſerve my pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe. And I thought it of grét pleaſure and uſe, not only to conceive theſe things my ſelf the moſt ſimply and diſtinctly, but alſo to be underſtood clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by others of more cloſe attention and reaſoning; and therefore by your ſelf in the firſt place, whoſe Command I very well re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member. If the Senſe and Notions as they are here de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:61142:77"/>be well comprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, as I hope they may with a little uſe, it will be eaſie for men of Style, as they have occaſion, to make for them, and put them in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a more faſhionable dreſs, and to expreſs them by more tunable talk, for the ſake of thoſe, who either wanting Ability, or ſhunning Pains, or admiring Elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, Fancy, and Wit, more than Truth and Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinctneſs and Uſefulneſs of Knowledge, are content and beſt pleaſed with a general, confuſed, and figurative ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion,
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:61142:77"/>or with a ſmooth, modiſh, and affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onate expreſſion of things. Nor are they indeed to be neglected, being the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rality of men, who though they have little Appetite to Naked Senſe, and dry Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, the food of ſtrong and ſound Minds; yet will very well receive, and digeſt it too, for uſe and action, when it is garniſhed and ſweetned in ſuch manner, as uſeth to be moſt acceptable and grateful to them.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:61142:78"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:61142:78"/>
            <head>Theſe Books following are publiſhed by the ſame Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor, <hi>G. Bright,</hi> D. D.</head>
            <p>A Treatiſe concerning Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing one another: Being ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Diſcourſes on the occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of our Saviour's Precept, Matth. 7.1. <hi>Judge not, that you be not judged.</hi> in
<hi>Octavo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Treatiſe of Prayer, with ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral uſeful occaſional Obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and ſome larger Digreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions concerning the Judaical obſervation of the Lords day, the external Worſhip of God. In <hi>Octavo.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:61142:79"/>
            <p>Tabulae Moſaicae Duae: Quarum Altera Precepta Legis Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaicae commodâ Methodo Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpoſita; altera oblationum om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nium, ex Efficiente, Materiâ, Conſumptione, Perſonis ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catu, Tempore, Diſtributiones varias continet. <hi>All Three ſold by</hi> John Wright
<hi>at the Crown on</hi> Ludgate-hill.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <list>
               <item>PAge 8. line 14. read <hi>think it.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Page 32. l. 16. r. <hi>kinds.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Page 38. l. 11. r. <hi>Momentany.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Page 39. l. 16. r. <hi>Momentany.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Page 50. l. 16. r. <hi>Beneficence.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Page 62. l. 9. r. <hi>Biberius.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <pb facs="tcp:61142:79"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
